soft & jeering radio episode 139 Linda
rising on fearless change this is
software engineering radio the podcast
for professional developers on the web
at se - radio dotnet as the radio brings
you relevant and detailed discussions
and interviews on software engineering
topics every two weeks thanks to our
audience and the partners listed on our
web site for supporting the podcast
hello everybody
Marcus here I want to talk to you
regarding a couple of hopefully
interesting things first of all as a
radio is now more than three years old
it has changed quite a bit from being a
podcast where the team talks about their
own experience to a mostly interview
podcast interview podcasts are quite a
bit more work and since the team is also
stressed and some people have dropped
out or can't contribute as much as they
plan to we are really running at the
limits of our capacity so that's why we
have decided to go from a every ten day
to a every two week rhythm so from now
on se radio will publish its episodes
every fourteen days and not every ten
days I realized that some people of
course don't like that I don't either
but I guess you know you can to keep
things sustainable we need to get the
workload to a level where it is
you know feasible for everybody to
continue contributing so that's one
measure also even with that it seems
like we would like to have one or two
additional team members team members
with that I mean people who interview
other people and produce the content so
that would mean that you that you
actually have access to interesting
people through conferences or something
you prepare interviews by discussing the
topics with you know the other team
members of as your radio you then record
the interview and then you edit the
interview regarding content sound
editing you don't
have to do you know cleaning up a sound
and and normalizing things that's what
Christie does and follicle then
publishes the episode and stuff so by
the way thanks for doing that and you
would have to have audio equipment that
allows you to record the audio in a
decent quality level so you know the
audience although in the beginning we
did have our problems with audio I think
we're now at a quite good level of audio
quality and time we want to keep that so
if if you're interested in you know
becoming part of the team
please well contact us at team at se
radio dotnet expect that we want you to
do a prototype interview first we really
want to make sure that you well you know
that that you that you that actually you
know can do that and that you're kind of
willing to put the work into it that
that needs to be put into it two other
things one is that together with her
Stefan took off Christian Bale and Mira
I have started another podcast on
software architecture it is German
language so if you don't speak German
you should probably skip the next minute
you can find the podcast at Heiser
developer that is at WWII CIA slash
developer slash podcast we have already
published a bunch of episodes and well
go give it a try the last comment I want
to make is just remind you of my Omega
at our podcast where I you know doing
all doing all the non software stuff
that I find interesting I mentioned that
on su radio before but for some reason I
only got like I don't know 100 or 200
listeners and I was expecting more here
because I thought if you listen to se
radio you might also want to listen to
other technology and science stuff we
have episodes on on airliner maintenance
and cryptography on music production on
radiation science at es RF and
aerodynamics on migratory birds
chocolate production so some of the
episodes are German some are English but
I guess you might want to give it a try
it
Omega tau podcast dotnet that's Oscar
Mike acaba of alpha tango alpha uniform
podcast dotnet okay so so much for the
advertising I just wanted to give you a
heads up we are going to continue an SEO
radio but we are going to continue at a
somewhat reduced pace I hope that's okay
with all you guys if not well well I
guess you can always help out and
contribute which makes our life easier
and well I guess but I think it's okay
there are many other podcasts available
now on software so you should be able to
fill your iPod
thanks and now let's get on with the
content of this episode welcome
everybody
you might be surprised that I'm here but
this is one of the sessions that are
co-produced between the ASU radio
podcast and your P conference so you
will be able to hear the discussion on
the podcast and you will be able to ask
questions and you'll be able to hear
yourself on the podcast which of course
requires that you actually ask questions
so I would recommend or you know I would
like to ask you to while we do the
discussion the beginning think about
what additional stuff you want to ask
you'll have enough time at the end and
if you don't ask anything we have a plan
B but would actually prefer for you to
ask questions so we have a microphone
and I'll walk around and you can then
ask questions and I'm just going to you
know I'll basically take the slides
reformulate the headings into questions
so that the guys listening to the
podcast have a way to connect to what's
going on okay
so I guess before we get started it's
time for you Linda to introduce yourself
okay thank you Marcus and thank you for
recording this because I know anytime I
do an interview with you and it goes
live I get email from all over the world
so you must have an incredible audience
and they all say I heard you on software
engineering radio so how exciting so my
name is Linda rising and I'm an
independent consultant I live in Phoenix
Arizona where according to my husband
the temperature today is 80 degrees so
that's 25
and this morning when I woke up I saw
snow we don't have snow in Phoenix
Arizona so what a treat to be here in
Munich so I'm interested in patterns
that's what we're gonna be talking about
today also retrospectives the change
process and agile software development
I'm very happy to be here I love to do
interviews with Markus and I love to
talk about patterns that's right okay so
let's get to the point so so the talk or
the discussion or whatever is about
patterns that help an organization to
become agile and I guess before we
actually talk about the specific
patterns it's probably useful to briefly
you know about what patterns are in the
first place so so let's take a little
poll I know that our listeners can't
participate but let me ask the audience
who's here today how many of you already
know something about patterns now how
many of you are actually using patterns
the gang of four patterns poza patterns
uh-huh
so we have a patterns literate audience
excellent so that must be a useful thing
for you patterns yeah good so that's the
idea I think those of us who were in the
patterns community at the beginning said
we want to document good ideas not just
from a theoretical standpoint these
should be things that are based on
experience and they should be useful
things so the idea is you document
well-known solutions based on the
experience of experts and then you give
the pattern a name now the power of a
name is that you can refer then to that
solution by name and hopefully if you
had enough patterns for your particular
domain you could have a collection of
names that all work together and we call
that a pattern language so the idea is
not just the search for the ultimate
pattern it's the search for the
collection of pattern
that work together to solve problems in
a particular domain so that's something
we were all introduced to in 1994 with
the Gang of Four patterns and for me it
was a transforming event because at that
point I think I caught the patterns
disease I see patterns everywhere so
there patterns in this room even as we
speak
so I'm always looking at patterns and
thinking about patterns so it was a
natural when my co-author Mary Lynn
Mane's who's also a patterns fanatic we
decided to write the book naturally it
should be a book of patterns just one
comment the podcast audience probably
also familiar we had the first episode
ever was on patterns or maybe cost a
second and we have 27 thousand downloads
about that so we can assume that the
people who listened to it also know
about it
so you mentioned the Gang of Four as
being the first you know use of patterns
in the software community but there is
of course prior art outside software and
that's Alexander stuff right Christopher
Alexander so look we we know that we
have a patterns literate audience we
have a lot of people here who are using
patterns let's do another poll we'll see
how many of you have heard of
Christopher Alexander look at that wow I
am impressed so Christopher Alexander
was a building architect oh wait how
many of you are using Christopher
Alexander's patterns gotcha okay so my
favorite of Christopher Alexander's
patterns the one I use the most as an
example
you won't find in this room it's called
light on two sides now this is a very
nice room and it does have natural light
coming in on one side and it's certainly
an extensive side but Alexander's
patterns suggest that all rooms should
have light natural light coming in on at
least two sides could be on adjacent
side
or opposite sides one of the sides could
be the ceiling we have a lot of
skylights in Arizona because we don't
like a lot of glass it gets to be 120
degrees in the summertime so we don't
want to encourage any more Sun than we
have to
so Christopher Alexander was writing
patterns for building architecture he
designs towns cities university campuses
corporate structures and after a while
he says I'm seeing the same thing over
and over again wouldn't it be nice to
document these common solutions gives
them a name and then we can refer to
them by that name so his two classic
books that we all point to even as
software developers are at the timeless
way of building and a pattern language
and it was interesting in the interview
with Tom DeMarco this morning that he
talked about Edie ordens rep referring
to Christopher Alexander's work in the
early 70s and saying this is what we
should all be looking at and the book
that he mentioned was the timeless way
of building in a pattern language and
said we should all be reading these
books so that was something I hadn't
realized certainly Tom DeMarco mentioned
Christopher Alexander in his people
where book which is now 25 years old so
long before the Gang of Four book there
were people who were looking at
Christopher Alexander they weren't
writing patterns for software yet but
they were thinking about it as a
direction in which we might head so I've
got Christopher Alexander's definition
of what a pattern is a pattern is
something that can be used over and over
again a million different ways without
ever doing it the same way twice so so
let's move over to your patterns okay
what's the story behind it history how
did they come about so I was working at
a medium-sized telecom company and I
went to Uppsala in nineteen
94 I don't how many of you were there at
Uppsala in 1990
how many of you were alive in 1994
oh that's good see that's only about
half the room do you notice that yeah
how so in 1994 at Uppsala which is a big
object-oriented conference it was even
bigger than oo P at the time not anymore
not anymore
but I went to that conference it was one
of my favorite conferences and there was
something new that year there were four
guys giving a tutorial on something
called design patterns so I went to the
tutorial and during that tutorial they
kept saying Ah the book is coming out
just wait tomorrow when the exhibit hall
opens the book is coming out and you'll
get a chance to buy the book so in those
days meadow
saw there was a huge huge exhibit
collection and a lot of those exhibits
were books ah the good old days
so in Addison Wesley's booth there were
stacks and stacks of the design patterns
book and people began lining up so the
line went from the addison-wesley booth
in the exhibit hall all the way out the
door of the exhibit hall and down and on
into the street you weren't there well I
was I was never in boarding school so
they outsold by a factor of 10 any other
book that's ever been introduced at a
technical conference no wonder Addison
Wesley loves patterns books they don't
sound like that anymore
no so I took that book back to my
company and I began to introduce the
idea of patterns and at that point I
became interested in
yes the patterns themselves but the
bigger questions of how do you get
people to look at your new idea how do
you convince people to use a new
technology or follow a new process
because that's what I was trying to do
how do you convince people that this is
a good thing
so I met Mary Lynn manse at a conference
about that time and she was trying to do
the same thing and between the two of us
we realized that there must be patterns
for introducing patterns and that was
the start how do you introduce patterns
and how do you document those successful
strategies for introducing patterns so
we began writing a book we began looking
at well how have people introduced new
ideas in the past talking to other
people who were trying to do the same
thing collecting stories we were really
trying to write patterns based on the
experience of other people who had done
the same thing now we started in in 1998
the book was not published until 2005
takes a long time to write patterns you
know that so the patterns are about as
you said introducing stuff into
organizations nuisance and there is a
little bit more specific context right
it's not like I'm the boss and I tell
you to use this stuff yeah different you
know I just read an article in Harvard
Business Review which I never was
interested in before and he talked about
a high-level executive of a very large
American company and he was asking the
question how do I introduce new ideas
and what he found out was there's a very
simple answer for some people you say if
we were going to do this or I will fire
you
that works so he said I'm very
successful in introducing new things I
just say what we're going to do and
people who don't line up unfortunately
we don't all have the ability to do that
and there is an interesting thing that
occurs if that high-level executive ever
leaves become the boss which is that
once that high-level executive leaves
people go back to do the same thing they
have always done so he got something
that I will call compliance he didn't
get commitment he didn't get the hearts
of the people in his organization
involved in the new idea in other words
he hadn't convinced anybody to do
anything and they were only lining up as
long as they had to so he realized
clearly that that wasn't what we wanted
not only did we not have the power we
wanted real commitment so we became
interested in how is it that you help
open people's minds to your ideas that's
what we wanted how is it that you get
them to see that you're sincere and that
you care about this new idea in fact
that turned out to be a pattern if
you're not sincere and if you don't care
you're not going to be convincing and
people will not open up to you so long
after the book was published a lot of
people who are experts in psychology
said you know these are interesting
patterns the reason why they work is
they are sitting on a body of knowledge
that comes from experiments that have
been done in social psychology I didn't
even know there was a field called
social psychology it's the study of the
psychology of groups how do you move
groups in a given direction so now
that's my passion
social psychology cognitive psychology
evolutionary biology all those ologies
so the target well you can read it so
still have to ask question right so the
target audience for the for the patterns
is what you call the powerless leader
yes we we stole that and in fact almost
all the ideas in there are borrowed or
stolen from other people and in fact
that would be my first piece of advice
for all of you steal from the best I
think most ideas need to be stolen and
reinvented and Reese said and adapted to
your own environment so you shouldn't
feel bad about that so we stole that
from norm curse he's one who created
German terminology powerless leader that
someone who isn't anointed who doesn't
have a high-level position in an
organization can still be a leader so
that's our target user as we were
writing the patterns we thought we want
the person who picks these up and uses
them to be someone in an organization
who is just like us an ordinary
developer someone who has a great idea
someone who can't even if he or she
wanted to who can't say you must do this
or I'm going to fire you so it's someone
without any power and we got an
interesting comment from someone who
does have power and a pretty large
organization in fact she was a vice
president and she said Linda I think you
can safely say that we are all powerless
at any level so I stole that - okay
so then I guess the the first thing that
you need except for thing of that slide
is to be really passionate about what
you want to do exactly that's the first
pattern now there isn't any set path
through the language you can use the
patterns in almost any order but the
very first one must be evangelists now
we argued a lot about that name yeah
right because my friend Mary Lin lives
in the south and she said Linda when I
hear the word evangelist I think of
things that I'd rather not think about
yes but on the other hand it is a
corporate term in fact we stole that
from Lucent
yeah I was working in a subsidiary of
Lucent at the time said the idea of a
corporate evangelist is an acceptable
term but we did go back and forth on
that one and we finally settled on it it
does have a religious flavor and as it
turns out there is a connection because
it has to do with faith it has to do
with faith in the idea and it also has
to do with faith in yourself because if
you're going to be convincing to others
if you want to introduce your idea into
your organization and I guess our target
here the title of this session is about
agile practices you can't do that unless
you honestly believe that agile
development whether you're a fan of
scrum or XP you have to believe that
it's a better way and you have to
believe that you have the ability to
help your organization by introducing
that so there is a religious component
the first person you have to convince is
yourself now there are lots of people in
here that I recognize who were in the
tutorial on Monday
where we actually went through a lot of
these patterns and at the end of that
tutorial what I've started doing now
that's very strange is helping people
understand that these patterns are not
just good for organizational change they
are also good for personal change so
that if you have a goal for yourself we
all make new year's resolutions is that
something you do in in this country make
new year's resolutions yeah I'm going to
run a marathon or never happens no it
never happens I'm gonna lose 50 pounds
I'm going to stop eating apple strudel
with vanilla sauce you're the one who
did that you're the one who told me yes
you have to have that always wonderful
hmm there are so many things we want to
do we have big goals and we make new
year's resolutions and it turns out
research tells us that those goals
last two months on average and then we
give up so the story I tell is about
people who have had a serious heart
attack or heart illness or heart surgery
and they go in to see their doctors and
the doctor says you have a choice you
can either change your life and that
means watch your diet start exercising
reduce the stress in your life stop
smoking or you can die now that's a
serious decision so here's the question
what percentage of the people who are
given that ultimatum are able to
successfully change themselves change
their own lives what percentage have a
number
seventy percent can change you say
$15.99 zero ten were you in the class
the answer is ten percent now I don't
know what goes through the conscious
minds of the other 90% well no I think
I'll die surely not surely it must be
something else
surely it must be I don't believe I can
because that percentage was so small
that researchers began investigating and
it turns out there's an inability to
apply this very first pattern in
changing their own lives they don't
truly deeply sincerely believe they can
change it's also a good segue into the
next question because it takes clearly
rationally you know you have to change
you try to convince people it should be
enough to tell them you know that's the
way that obviously this is the right
thing to do but still it's not enough to
change people so so what's missing no I
think that we all make this mistake and
in fact as my husband says when you're
reading through this slide or similar
ones I'm trying to convince myself
because I still believe this I'm reading
it now we're smart we make logical
decisions the people we work with are
also smart they make logical decisions
all I need to do is create a rational
argument maybe a set of PowerPoint
bullets or a conversation where I
outline clearly step by step why just
like the doctor is doing for his patient
clearly you have to do these things or
else
that's the rational argument isn't it
and we have an incredible amount of
faith in that as an influencer strategy
so just after I've said all of that how
many of you are believers in rational
argument as an influencer strategy good
for you oh okay okay so what see did you
see that pattern once he had his hand up
other people it all it takes is one
person and then we can all line up so we
do believe that now there are some
people who are looking for information
there are some people who want
information and you should be prepared
to present that information but it is
not an influencer strategy it does not
influence people to change and the
clearest evidence of that is the doctor
cut clear logical rational reasons why
well here's how many of you are smokers
oh come on I know there are more because
I've been sitting on that second floor
gathering over there
yeah you know rationally this is not a
good thing for you
you know rationally logically you're
cutting your own life short you are
saying I guess I'll die I would rather
die so it doesn't work as an influencer
strategy something I read or heard
probably heard in some kind of podcast
somewhere is that when you try to
convince somebody of something you
shouldn't explain the rationale stuff
but always try to make it or explain it
in a way that it explains why it is a
benefit to them so you have to you know
have a target audience and then say for
you what this means this for you
this means that well that of course
that's an important part of it I think
but the other part is realizing that
people accept new ideas including I mean
there were 10%
who were able to change so there are a
small number of people who are open to
certain kinds of things and what we want
to realize is that in your organization
you're going to run into different kinds
of people so if you come in with the
idea of doing scrum or XP whatever your
favorite agile process is there are some
people who only need you to say hey I
went to Hopi I went to a session by
who's doing a session here on agile
development I heard somebody famous
talking about this new cool thing and
I'm thinking maybe this would be good
for our organization and those people
only need that and they say sign me up
so those are the innovators they love
new ideas think about your organization
think about the people you could just
walk up to and say hey I went to Opie
and here's a book or some kind of
article or here's what a famous person
said and this is the latest the newest
the coolest the hottest thing and that's
it they're ready they'll pair program
they'll start doing time-boxed
iterations they'll do daily stand-ups it
doesn't matter what it is they'll do it
so it doesn't take a PowerPoint slide
for them those are the low-hanging fruit
but they'll talk about it to all their
friends so don't avoid those don't just
say oh I don't have to do anything for
the innovators they come for free use of
them let them help you because they'll
talk it up with all their friends so
those are the innovators but see how
small the percentages in an average
population only two and a half percent
that's an ordinary typical I've never
seen an ordinary typical organization
now that I think about it
so this is a standard curve so not very
many certainly you could probably find
organizations where you'd have 50% of
the people who are innovators so the
next large group is early adopters now
they would like to see the PowerPoint
slide sounds interesting
tell me more oh maybe that could help us
I'd like to ask some questions do you
have an article I could read oh you say
you bought a new book I'd like to take a
look at that so they do want information
they are open to new ideas but they
would like to see more the next large
categories early majority and if you'll
notice what convinces them is what other
people think and it's people in their
own like local people they know or my
friends my neighbors colleagues
colleagues yes so it's going to take a
few either pilot projects or tests you
want to see what other people in their
organization think of it to see whether
it really applies to them and then oh
okay I hear the project x over there
project Y over here they're doing agile
it seems to work for them they're open
to new ideas
it just takes something different to
convince them which is evidence close to
home people just like me that I can
identify with so they're not going to be
the first ones on the block to buy a new
gadget they wait till their neighbors
have it where their friends are using it
that's actually a significant part of a
of a normal population it's over a third
are like that and then the late majority
see what the comment is there I'll do it
if I have to so only when your
organization is already doing agile and
now there is somebody who has a certain
level of authority who said
is really working for us we're all going
to do scrum okay I'll do it if I have to
I guess and then there are the laggards
it's always been done this way why do we
have to do something new now man it will
take a poll again how many managers how
there's kind of common occurrences and I
had managers always ask at this point
how can I identify those people so
that's very important actually because I
remember the first time that question
came up and I thought I did not do a
good job because these are not people
these are roles people play these roles
at different times so they are more or
less open to a new idea depending upon
the idea so someone might be an
innovator for a technical idea but would
never eat sushi you know somebody like
that yeah nobody is an innovator all the
time and we also don't want to say that
there's a goodness scale good at the top
bad at the bottom so one of the projects
I worked on in my unfortunately very
long career was the triple 7 airplane
and Boeing said the triple 7 is all
going to be done in a de so that was
actually my job I was the ADA guru who's
trying to help people transition to a
new programming language and a new way
of design now all the airplanes up to
that time had been written in a funny
version of Pascal think about that the
next time you get on a 747
or fire bus but you see so who were
those people I had to work with on that
project
they all said exactly the same thing
it's always been done this way and
successfully the 747 is a successful
plane nobody would argue with that it's
still in service it's always been done
this way why do we have to switch and
they had a valid point and they were all
good people and they were all very smart
people and certainly triple7 could not
have been done without them I could not
have done anything on triple7 no matter
how much Aida I knew because I'm not a
domain expert I know a little more than
I did but I'm not an avionics expert so
here were all of these individuals with
enormous amounts of experience and
knowledge very valuable you would not
want to label them as laggards and say
all right you guys are out of here so I
have to be careful it was a point of a
keynote a couple of days ago I said you
have to be careful about labeling people
so you're you're you're powerless you're
passionate yeah what do you do no you
have to be agile
oh okay to be agile that means and that
means that and this came much later
actually realizing that I'm not only
passionate about patterns I'm passionate
about agile so and I've talked to
several people here so I'm seeing if any
of those people are in the room I'm not
only a believer in agile for software
development
I believe in agile as a way of
introducing agile in fact I believe that
you should be agile about the way you
live your own life so I've been giving a
series of talks on personal agility and
a lot of it hangs on this what's called
a learning cycle people are coming to
this conference in other conference
and they're interested in agile
development and they're asking the same
question how can I make it happen how
can I roll out the old and roll in the
new as though it were a binary decision
a switch yes we do agile now when really
it's a process of learning just like
life is a process of learning just like
agile has turned software development
into a process of learning it's made up
of little tiny steps little short
iterations and in each iteration it is
about learning that is the primary goal
you and the customer are learning
together and at the end of every step
you stop and you ask the question what
have we learned so far and on the basis
of that you take the next step that's
how you develop software that's how you
introduce agile step by step go back
home on Monday morning and try something
some small thing and when you do it say
we're only going to do this for two
weeks four weeks a month whatever it is
time boxes just as agile development is
time box time box that experiment and at
the end we're saying we're going to look
at this in four weeks and we're going to
ask the question what did we learn will
this work for us what seems to work
especially well that we should continue
doing what might not work so well that
we might need to tweak or adjust what
should we do next
sounds like a retrospective it does
sound like a retrospective yeah so
that's part of the pattern language that
turned out to be critical piece that
says that's how you should introduce
everything gradually step by step I'm
not a believer in whole
sail change and people often point out
there's a book by Malcolm Gladwell I
don't know whether you've read it's
called the tipping point oh yeah it
makes it sound like things get to a
point and then Wow which i think is true
but how did that tipping point appear
just suddenly out of nowhere now it was
approached by a meandering path a very
small what's the topic here stepping
stones is a very small stepping stone
and at some point one of those stepping
stones led to an enormous upheaval and
all of a sudden the organization said
yes or everyone started buying hush
puppies that's Malcolm Gladwell's
example so yeah that that's a
possibility step by step and then all of
a sudden yeah you're gonna you're ready
to run that marathon but that can't be
your goal because you don't know when
that's going to happen you have to
continually learn I guess it's also a
little bit about timing that you can
kind of sense when the time is right for
an idea absolutely it's almost as though
you know what's coming yeah well you
know how do you do that good timing
sometimes it's just not right I don't
know about you but the United States is
struggling right now even though we have
a new president thank you God we're
struggling it's hard now for a lot of
organizations to think about any kind of
change we might have to wait until the
time is right there's so many good ideas
that failed just because they appeared
at a moment that was inopportune that's
true for all of history whatever flavor
medical history the history of science
a wonderful idea appeared but it was not
quite ready
sometimes it takes decades hundreds of
years before that idea can actually have
impact so I have to have a sense of your
own organization your own team your own
life the timing has to be just right so
don't give up if you do go back and
you're enthusiastic you have passion and
you're going to take a few small steps
and it leads nowhere might just be as
simple as well let's wait six months
maybe the world will be a better place
in six months I hope give us some very
concrete hands on our little joke here
yeah so concrete's that's what can I do
to make it easier for me so there I'll
give you some concrete examples of
patterns from the pattern language some
things that you can try when you go back
on Monday morning you want to take a
little small step put could that small
step be so here's my favorite it's
called brown bag and we all have our
favorite names for these so it's
culturally dependent what would you call
that in Germany well bag brown bag is
you don't have a brown bag that we use
the term also Oh something you say
wrestle me oh and and who is it somebody
does a scrum breakfast yeah that's all
right
that kind of thing for somebody brings
so we have you have food you all eat
together and you talk about your idea
and you invite anyone who wants to show
up you say well we're going to have this
whatever it is this breakfast or this
lunch or and and people will show up
with their food the brown bag comes from
the US
have it people used to bring their
sandwich in a little paper bag the goal
damn and they would and they would eat
lunch together so you talk about scrum
or what you know or what a great time
you had it Opie or whatever it is now
the reason why that works is interesting
it started out as a pattern because we
were all using it and then the cognitive
scientists got into the act and they
said here's what's going on why that
pattern works is that we have evolved
over tens of thousands of years to trust
people when we are sharing food think
about what it must have been like on the
Savannah and Africa I know you can't
remember back that far and neither can i
[Laughter]
the only people who shared food with us
were the people we knew very well our
close associates our family our friends
so it builds trust right it's not the
idea it the idea is that you trust those
people that the trust and the food are
linked in our minds so the experiment I
like to tell about it is the political
one where they're trying to convince
people to vote on a particular issue so
they took two groups of people one group
got food the other one didn't who voted
for the issue the one with the food yes
and then the next thing I say is it has
nothing to do with the quality of the
idea it does have to do with the quality
of the food okay yes yes so if people
are eating food that you brought or
you're sharing and it's not what was
that Apple stuff with the vanilla not
that it's some some other artificial
like me today well I don't know I didn't
I
the food affects the quality of the
decision quality of the food is related
not the idea itself so for a lot of
people have startling and then the
question I ask is do you think it's
possible for people who know all these
patterns and all the influencer
strategies to use them so effectively
that they could convince people of ideas
that are inherently bad you want to
think about that can a master a master
influencer sway an entire country so
that people do bad things
absolutely and it's happened over and
over again so don't get carried away
with your idea and believe that somehow
the idea is enough you have to have the
the patterns the tools to help you kind
of discouraging in a way isn't it well
but no doesn't it doesn't it's not a bad
thing you actually have a good idea
if you have a good idea then you you
definitely need the tools so brown bag
means you can have people bring their
own food do food means well if you
bought some apple strudel or chocolate
chip cookies or whatever then you're
sharing food together that's the
important part is we want to eat
together and have people eat while
they're listening to you which also
prevents them from talking
so it puts them in a good mood and don't
be afraid
just go back and try something just do
it so just pick some piece of I'm not a
believer in wholesale change and I am a
scrum fan so when I talk to people I say
just go back and start having a daily
stand up and say this is a scrum
practice and there are three questions
that people address takes 15 minutes for
the meeting just try that just do it see
how it works for you and remember when
you set it up you're going to say well
let's just try it say this to your team
we're going to do it for time box it and
then say what you're gonna look for at
the end so we're gonna try this for a
couple of weeks and then we're gonna say
well how did that work for us what did
you notice what changes happened in the
team because we were doing that just do
it you don't need to be afraid I'm a fan
of study groups what do you call that
here oh so I'm a fan of study groups for
anything that you're learning about and
your new idea is probably something that
you need to learn more about or that
others the early adopters need to know
about so it basically involves getting
no more than eight people together once
a week to just go through a book or read
a paper together to get more information
it's good for early adopters trying to
make people ask questions with the stage
you know is anybody who want to ask
questions we have 15 minutes left if you
don't ask questions we do have material
if you want her to continue talking you
just don't ask questions but so I give
you the chance for another five seconds
to actually raise your hand and ask a
question or let make me come to you to
give you the mind
I doubt it
I'm later on I could you give her five
five seconds uncompressed version off
the session I hope there was a joke
but the good thing is be recalling that
so you can actually I was gonna say you
can get the podcast yes you can download
the whole thing but uh excellent any
other questions
I mean uh okay then Linda I think we
have to just continue well work well I
just haven't in at any time raise your
hand and I'll be happy to have you ask a
question yes that was the original idea
to have audience I think you're too
convincing so score scary yeah okay so I
have to fake a question right which is
what can go wrong what can go wrong
yeah yes they're a danger isn't doing
that there are dangers and I I have
personal touch here but I'm going to see
if if the real danger is in here
somewhere but maybe not so I'm gonna ask
I'm gonna say what I think the real
danger is regardless of what's here the
good thing is most people don't see them
that's right yes so here's the real
danger okay so after the book came out I
saw a fellow at a conference and he came
up to me and he said hello Linda I
bought bought your book I said hope
thank you
I said I read all those patterns wow
that's good honey said they don't work
by themselves I told him it oh I'm
always happy to get feedback I said well
tell me your story
what happened so here's the danger part
so he started talking about using the
patterns and as he was talking I had a
vision I had a dream
I saw a man coming into an organization
riding a white horse and he was looking
down at the people in the organization
saying all you people you ignorant
people listen to me I have the answer I
know the one true way I will lead you
out of your misery into the Promised
Land I heard music to dream the
impossible dream I don't know why he
wasn't successful it was all about him
yeah
so the pattern maybe it's in the next
slide I don't know it's called ask for
help it's called ask for help most
people who go in to an organization are
just a little arrogant I know this
answer I see all of these problems I
have the solution and they can so easily
be carried away with the fact that they
have a little secret or a little
knowledge or little information and
they're so convinced because they are
passionate they do believe and so they
cross the line from evangelist to
fanatic and that is not convincing and
it turns people off so you must
constantly you must always be on the
lookout for that and the only solution
to that problem is to bring others in so
it's not about you so the pattern is
called ask for help your job and
spreading the word is not
I will tell you it's I need you to help
me you need the help of everyone in the
organization somehow and that is the
most convincing thing that you can do is
let them have a little piece of it let
them own the idea let them feel ah
I see how this can work for me let them
be the one to talk at the next Brown Bag
or be the one to introduce it in the
next organization or experiment it with
it on their team let them give the talk
let them share the recognition if this
is a project that becomes you carrying
the word it'll just be like the guy at
the conference and those patterns don't
work get off your white horse so before
you even get on while you're still
thinking about it and remember the
anecdote just ask for help it's also a
convincing thing it's an influence
strategy if you ask for help from people
and they do something for you there's
something that goes on in their brain
that says oh I'm doing this I must like
scrum or whatever it is oh we're doing
the daily stand-ups
we must like the daily stand-ups so it's
also a very convincing influence
strategy to just say hey would you like
to and then involve them somehow and
then also say thanks if you actually get
the help absolutely yes
so this is a very important pattern that
goes along with ask for help whenever
you ask somebody for help you should
always say thank you and it seems
trivial doesn't it yeah yeah you talked
about this yesterday even in your bar
it's not just so Thanks a very specific
thing has to be specific it has to be
thank you for doing something on
because I couldn't do it and it's not
just thanks and but here's the really
important message about just say thanks
which is something we finally left in
because so many people said we've
forgotten this
nobody says thank you anymore
they either assume that well it's part
of your job it's expected so even when
you do more than you should or you you
come in over the weekend or you give up
something personally for your job say I
don't mind doing that it is part of my
job nobody said thanks so here's the
interesting thing about the pattern that
we learned long effort err was published
there's gratitude research can you
imagine that being a research topic
gratitude shows that people who do this
who are pattern users who go around
saying thanks Marcus this is a lot of
fun thank you for inviting me for this
interview who do that all the time it's
just part of the way they are they are
grateful people those people live longer
sign me up
they have fewer colds or colds and flues
they're more likely to achieve their
personal and professional goals so let
me just take this opportunity to thank
all of you thank you I don't know that
there's been any research there but I'm
not taking any chances
so you might try using that pattern
anyway just appreciate I'll tell you
what's interesting is I started using
this on my husband
talk about a surprised individual I said
hey thanks for doing that would we say
thank you to our spouse to our children
our parents our parents just a
suggestion so it's probably going to
happen that you still will run into
resistance people won't you know won't
follow you so what do I do with skeptics
so our natural inclination oh no this is
the most important oh no I didn't good
our natural inclination is to run away
or or to avoid those people after all
they must be ignorant they're not paying
any attention yeah those people are
stupid they're not listening go get it
they don't get it so the fear last
pattern is less for the name of the book
comes from fear less change and it's
talking about that tendency that we have
to avoid criticism it's a natural thing
we don't want to hear especially if
we're passionate and enthusiastic we
don't want to hear the downsides we
don't here are those negative
consequences and unfortunately that is
valuable information especially I would
say for someone who's new to agile and
you're excited about it there's
something about the way your brain works
that you will fail to see a lot of the
negative consequences a lot of the
places where there isn't a good match
where it might be totally inappropriate
where it might not work for you it's
much better if you can have someone who
might even be well intentioned point out
some of those things to you before you
get hip-deep in something that isn't
going to work I would listen if I had
someone who was willing to spend time
with me pointing out some of those
difficulties I'm not saying that's an
easy thing to do I guess if it's if it's
like rational criticism it's easier than
if you have two guys to trust it's all
crap I don't care I mean you're talking
about those skeptics not about the like
politically motivated I don't care if
I'm lucky you know that's an interesting
thing because most of the time
regardless of what the person is saying
that's what we hear
that's crap I don't care about what you
have to say when really what they're
saying is you know we tried doing
something like that and they're they're
sincere they really did we did try this
and it didn't work because and that you
don't even hear that yeah you have
filtered that out and all you're hearing
is this guy's an idiot and all he's
telling me is agile is crap that's
really all you hear that's all you
register so it takes a certain amount of
work on your part to get past that to
say what is he saying to really listen
to what he's saying because our tendency
is not only to avoid people like that
but filter it so that we even distort
the words if someone were to come up to
us and say well what did he just tell
you often we're totally unable to do
that I don't really hear the words that
person is saying you know I have a
question that's maybe he's going to say
something about fearless hopefully okay
I remember professor Duke in his speech
when he talked about the point of how do
I motivate as a techie how do I motivate
managers to do what I want and what I
need and he talked about people who
repeatedly say no this is not possible
in this company this company doesn't
work that way how do I convince or how
do I get those people and he recommended
to say hey listen I know that this is
illegal what I'm going to do
but you're the person who knows
perfectly about all the rules in this
company and I admire you for that and
please help me to make it legal this is
I thought this is genius it's a good way
to involve the skeptic it's a good way
of asking for help from the skeptic and
and many times if you really do a good
job of listening and you do pick out
something that they have as to make as a
contribution and involve them in that
way remember in the class we said well
if you've done everything you can and
you still can't find some way to involve
them you can just make them the champion
skeptic and say alright you you just
tell me all the things that are wrong
and that's good information in and of
itself but yes that's that's excellent
and at the heart of that or the pattern
in that is you want to involve them
somehow
bring them in and in fact I can remember
hearing and a lot of tutorials that
that's a common argument that this won't
work here because it's illegal or we did
it before or that's all valuable
information do everything you can to
extract that and use it just like a
lawyer does in preparing his case you
want to hear all of that so we have -
two minutes left so we should get
towards the end so is there anything
well how do we wrap this up I don't know
well is there enough I can't run what's
a conclusion summary yeah we so there's
a book about all this and of course I'd
be happy if you bought if you buy the
book but if you remember the first slide
and you do have these slides right you
can go to my website and I've written so
many articles about it that you can pick
out the essence of the book by just
downloading a bunch of those articles
and reading them and the other thing
that's on that first slide is my email
address and if you didn't get to ask a
question today or for listeners yeah you
weren't here to ask a question I love to
talk about patterns and change and agile
development so please feel free I'm
sincere send me some email I'd love to
hear from you thanks for being here
today thanks for being and
thanks for listening to software
engineering radio software engineering
radio is an educational program brought
to you by hillside Europe if you want
more information about the podcast and
all the other episodes visit our website
at SE - radio dotnet if you want to
support us you can donate to the AC
radio team via the website or you can
advertise for SI radio for example by
clicking on the Digg reddit delicious
links and the select button to contact
the team please send email to team @ SE
- radio net or if it is specific to an
episode please use the comments facility
on the website so other people can react
to your comments this episode of se
radio as well as all other episodes are
licensed under the creative commons 2.5
license please see the website for
details thanks to Charlie Crowell and
the pot size Music Network for the music
used in this show the song is called
Vegas hard rock shuffle